Welcome to Day 3 of AntVent Of Code 2022.
Today's problem gives us a series of strings,
each string has an even number of elements,
which are letters of the English alphabet,
lowercase and uppercase.
What we have to do is, for each string,
find the letter,
and the fact that it is uppercase and lowercase is important,
so they are different,
which appears in the first and second half of each string.
There is always one and only one.
For example, in this case, we see that the lowercase p
appears only here and here,
so this is the letter we have to find.
For each string in this list we have to find this letter,
then we have to calculate a score corresponding to this letter.
The score will be, if the letter is lowercase,
a number that goes from 1 to 26 for all alphabet letters,
then the lowercase is 1 and the lowercase is 26,
if instead it is uppercase, we go from 27 to 52,
then the uppercase A is 27, the lowercase A is 28 and so on,
until we get to the Z, which is 52.
Today, to do things better,
I have already created the beginning of my problem,
so I have already set my code and I have already saved the file.
So we have a get_input function
that already provides us with the list of all these strings.
So the part 1, we can do it directly like this.
Let's start by creating a counter,
actually no, let's start with finding these letters that interest us,
so these repeated letters.
For each line, which we call a rucksack,
because this is what is represented by the line,
so a bag essentially,
in the input, so the input of the problem,
we have to find what is at the beginning and at the end of this...
we have to divide them in half,
so I say that L, which is a num for number,
is the length of the rucksack,
then I say look, part 1 is rucksack until nun
and part 2 is the rucksack from nun onwards.
I'm not sure of the indices, I never remember this,
so what do I do? I open my Python console
and I say look, rucksack is equal to abcdef, while at it,
nun is the length of the rucksack in this case will be 6
and part 1 will be equal to this thing here,
so part 1, (what...) which obviously I have to divide by 2,
indeed I do it directly here,
so number is this thing divided by 2,
here we arrive at noon and then from noon onwards we do this other thing,
so we try again, number is the length, so 3,
part 1 will be what?
Obviously we want the division that gives us the whole number,
so we do it again,
noon now is the whole number, 3,
and part 1 will be, let's see what it contains, abc, perfect,
while part 2 is from noon onwards and contains df, perfect.
At this point I want to find the letter in common,
taking advantage of the fact that a string in Python can be seen as a list of characters,
I can directly make a set with the letters of part 1,
make a set with the letters of part 2
and use an ampersand,
the iComampersandmercial for the set is simply a way of performing the operation intersect,
intersection, sorry,
intersection gives us the common elements between these two sets,
so take the two strings, the two pieces of string,
create a set and find the intersection,
this set will be composed of a single element,
so we call it common,
and at this point the letter that I found,
therefore the letter in common,
will be what?
It will be the only common element,
so I say assert length of common is 1,
I want to make sure there are no bugs,
and common is the set with that letter.
While at it, I can avoid creating a variable for part 1 and part 2,
but I use them directly.
Ok, and so I found the letter in common,
common is a string set,
I can find the letter in common saying that it is a list that derives from common,
because I cannot take an element only from the set,
I have to transform it into a list,
and then take the zero element.
Another thing I could do is iterate on the set,
let's say next,
we can try in the shell directly,
so next is set containing the letter a,
no,
I have to do something more complicated,
so I keep it like this, who cares,
I make a list,
so from the set of an element to a list of a single element,
I take the number zero,
so the only letter that is inside,
I made an assertion, so I already know that there is only one, so I'm sure,
and this is the first part, I found the letter.
Now I have to calculate the score,
so I create a variable int that contains the return value,
which will be zero initially,
here I will calculate the score in some way and then return ret,
this is the usual boilerplate way to calculate a sum.
Now I have to calculate the score assigned to a letter,
so I create a function that I will call item_value,
which given a letter l,
gives back an integer which is its value,
so the problem tells us that,
we directly copy the definition,
so it becomes directly a comment that I insert here,
I say ok look,
first of all I want to know if this letter is lowercase or uppercase,
so I say if L is lower, I think,
so is lower tells me if it is lowercase or uppercase,
I know that this is a single letter,
so I'm not worrying too much.
How do I do it?
I can create my dictionary or I can use the ord function,
which tells me the number of the code point that represents this character,
so each character has an associated number,
and for English alphabet letters these numbers are consecutive,
so I don't remember which one is minuscule,
we can see it,
but we are only interested in the difference,
so it's 97 for the lowercase and 98 and so on,
so I say look,
make a difference between the character we have here, ord of L, and the lowercase,
so we find a difference,
we find a position in the English alphabet,
and obviously we have to add 1,
because if it is the lowercase the ord code will be the same and the difference 0,
but we have to start from 1,
so we return this thing,
otherwise if it is uppercase we do the same thing,
but with the uppercase A of course,
and this time we don't add 1 anymore,
we don't add 1 but 27,
and that's it.
So now all we have to do is add ret, ret plus equal,
as we called it, item_value of letter,
and that's it,
so let's try to execute our exercise,
in fact let's do a nice pdm run black because we like it,
perfect,
pdm run also mypy strict because we are evil,
oh noes, there is a return that is missing here of course,
because we return minus 1,
in reality we don't care because this is the part 2 that we will implement later,
perfect,
and we execute our program,
so,
you hear the scream because of my neighbor,
so we have 7997,
perfect, this should be the solution,
if there are no errors, or maybe there are,
ok, correct,
well, let's move on to part 2,
blah blah blah,
so every group of 3 elves is the only one loaded with 3 elves,
so ok, to be quick we don't have to deal with the problem,
so let's see the first 3 lines are these here,
so the first group,
the only element that appears in all 3 is the lowercase R,
so we have to find an element that appears in 3 consecutive lines,
so 3 consecutive bags,
in the second group the common element is the capital Z,
blah blah blah,
ok, and the priority,
I think it's the same as before,
so the lowercase R is 18, so the function that gives us the value, we can find it,
and we have to find the sum of the priorities for each of these elements,
so basically we have to do the same thing that we did now,
but instead of working on half of these bags,
we have to work on groups of 3 bags,
and find the common element,
so for part 2, we brutally copy the code from part 1,
with the difference that, how do we do it,
let's create a nice index,
that works on a range that goes from 0,
0 can be omitted,
to the size of the input problem and with step 3,
the range function practically gives me all,
it's an iterator that goes from 0,
in this case, to the length of the input problem,
so it goes from 0 to how many elements I have,
with a step 3, so it will give me 0, 3, 6, 9 and so on,
and that's it, so now I want to find the 3,
I no longer have a rucksack, a line divided in 2,
but I have 3 consecutive lines,
what do I say?
in common I have,
which is actually easier to define,
I have problem_input at the position idx,
problem_input at the position idx plus 1,
and I have problem_input at the position idx plus 2,
I'm pretty sure this operator can be associated in this way,
and this is part 2, let's see if it's already correct,
let's run it,
so I copy this thing,
it's correct, good good good,
it was easier than expected,
bye everyone and see you next day.