Hello everyone and welcome to day 2 of the Advent of Code 2022. Today we have a
game of rock-paper-scissors and the description of the problem is a bit strange, in the sense that it talks
about a strategy and the input in theory defines a strategy, but in reality what it does is define a
list of games of rock-paper-scissors and the problem asks us to evaluate, to calculate what the
final result is. The final score is given by a series of points based on how many games I won or
ended up in a draw plus some points calculated based on which of the three possibilities I have
chosen, so for example if my opponent choses rock and I chose paper I get 8 points for
having won, which are given by 2 points for having chosen paper because paper is worth 2 in this case
plus 6 points for having won, so the input we have here is a list of letters that are for my
opponent A, B and C and for me X, Y and Z that represent rock, paper and scissors, so I have to copy this
input, I use the same structure as yesterday so I create a new file that I will call day02.txt,
I paste the input and this is it. Same thing for the python file, I create a new file that I call
day02.py, here I go to read the input, then I create a function that I will call get_input
which will return a string list
we could also make it become a list of tuples, we make strings and that's it, this
makes me read the file as I did yesterday, so in fact I copy the code from yesterday,
with open blah blah blah, I open the file and I read it, fr.readlines will give me all the
lines, they are a string list and for each one I want, in this case while at it, I eliminate the
central space because it does nothing, it has no advantage, this space that I have between
the two letters, so I make a nice return of the line, the first character and now the second,
nah, let's do replace, so it is very clear what we are doing, I am removing the space
for help in fr.readlines and that's it, I don't see any problem, since I have it, I do mypy,
ok, no problem, well, so let's create our usual control, if __name__ equals __main__, maybe tomorrow
I will write this part before the video, I take the input, so problem input will be get_input
and I pass it to the function that will be part 1 as yesterday, so I create two functions that
make part 1 and part 2, the result of this function will be a number, an integer,
and what does this function do? So it must calculate for each game, so for each pair of three letters
that will be my opponent and me, the score of that game, so this score is given by two elements,
which are the score given by the fact that I won or lost or evened out and the score given by what I
chose, how many possible combinations there can be in a game, the possible letters that
can be there, so in a row? are nine because there are three possibilities for what my opponent plays,
three possibilities for what I play and therefore three times three is nine, so nine possible
combinations, it means that there are so few that I can easily list them, I can list them and
calculate one by one what the result is, I can do this with a series of ifs, obviously feasible,
there are only nine, but it is easier and intuitive to do it with a dictionary, so I create a dictionary
that will be at the level of the module because maybe I will reuse it for part 2 because it will ask me
to calculate something like that and I can call this dictionary scores, I create a
good dictionary and here I can go and put all the combinations, so A equals something,
so I repeat three times, maybe I also put a comma that we say, then I will also put B equals
something obviously and since there are, I do the same thing with C, so I have C and then we can put the
combinations of x, y and z, so I use the multiple cursor and put one x, one y and one z, ok I have created all
the combinations that can be in a row, if I have something that is not in this dictionary it means
that there is an error, now here I could already put the score calculated according to the two rules,
so the rule that gives a score to the game and the rule that gives a score to the single element
that I have played, I prefer to keep them separate because you never know that part 2 asks me
a different criterion, so it makes me comfortable to already have the dictionaries separate, so I call it
gamescores to indicate that it is the score of how much a single game gives me, not the score given by
indeed no... no, nothing, I do gamescores, so this is how much a game gives me but only
for the fact that I have won or lost, then from another dictionary or another if for the score
of what I have played, now I have created all the combinations and then we proceed to give the
scores, what does it tell us where the hell it is here, what does it tell us about the score of the game that we take
0 if we lose, 3 if we even and 6 if we win, so I start with the draw that is 3 and here I say
if AX which means both have stone, BY which means both have paper and CZ which means both have
scissors, they are three points because we have evened the game I see it from the point of view of my
player so the second letter x y z and then we have that if the opponent plays a and I
have played y I have won so they are 6 points and therefore this other 0 if the opponent has played b
which is paper and I have played x which is stone the opponent has won so 0 points therefore the other
are 6 last combination cx if the opponent has played c which are scissors and I have played x
which is stone I have won so they are 6 points otherwise 0 we can control it for
sure that since I have always used the same order of letters the order of numbers is always different
so I have 360 036 603 perfect if you are wondering how I do to be so fast and safe when
I write these points it is because reading the problem before the video I made a sketch by hand
with the three scissors and paper scissors but I do not put it in a video because editing the video
requires a lot of time and I do not have enough visualizations to justify this effort
well then we have game scores which are the scores of the games maybe I create a comment
that says what this game score does so the score that derives from the game itself
the comment is not really clear in fact I can also
comment is not that adds a lot anyway I have it well now we want to do our calculation
now you can make a nice sum of a list comprehension and I think that is what I will do in fact
it does not seem quite complicated to me to request to decompose a loophole or something like that
I make a list comprehension and I'm fine so I create another dictionary that we call
how we call it this is the most difficult problem of informatics to give names to things we call it
move_score this is another dictionary that contains the three scores that obviously I forgot
for stone paper scissors so 1 is stone 2 is paper and 3 is scissors so 1 is stone 2 is paper and 3 is scissors
and now I want what the problem is asking us the total sum yes question we have to calculate the
score even when I lose yes so it is a simple sum there is no score of my move
is calculated even when I lose so they are completely unrelated I want to do the sum of what
of the score due to the game then game scores of the move of the game that we call p indeed
I call yeah, pi per play the same plus the move score of what of the second letter of the game
so 1 of p for each p in the input then the input is the list of the moves for each value this is a
comprehension for each value then for each pair of letters I take the result of the game
then this value here and sum the result in the move the move is calculated only based on what I
played so I have to take the second letter then p1 and this obviously I have to return it
maybe so and this is how much so I use mypy just for paranoia and black because
because no perfect and now I can finally run my code we follow day 2... oh no there is a small
problem you see that here we are keeping track of the newline because this read lines includes
even if here it does not say it the newline so I strip all the values ​​that are not characters
so white space that are at the end perfect so to recap this backslash n is simple
of the newline that is provided by read lines I never remember when I eliminate the newline no so
it is something that I generally ignore and solve when I see this problem so it gave me a number
and I put this number in the puzzle perfect let's see part 2 that I don't know this is always a
risk when you improvise but at most I cut the video of one part as I did last year in English
there is some story to add here it is what a mess it is?? x means that you lose ok
so the final point is always calculated in the same way but now you have to choose which
figure to choose ok I didn't know it was called a figure I will forget it in two minutes
the example goes like this so if your opponent chooses a stone but you choose no but you are y so you have to
even out you have to choose even you stone ok so this problem is totally disconnected from the
problem ok oh what a bad thing ok really bizarre we can only reuse a little piece
which is the value of the individual pieces so what do we have to do for part 2 we have to do
something really strange oh what a bad thing it feels like working with excel so it works like this if we
have for example let's see a concrete example from my file if I have c y the y is no longer indicated
is no longer the move I played but the result I want to get y means
even so x loss y is even and z victory this means that if I have a y here this
game will have to equalize so I will also have to play a c which is equal to scissors the score
I take for this game is simply the score of the scissors it does not matter if I come or lose
well then I simply have to calculate the values ​​for each possible combination which is a bit of a
mistake but we can do it so I call this case course 2 and here we have the joy of
understanding what we want to do so let's see with the x I mean that I have to lose so let's start
with the y which is the draw right because the y is the simplest case because if I draw
I simply have to play the same move of the other so what are the scores are still the same
before perfect or no I understood badly I still have to count the result ok so it seems a
bit of a bizarre situation because I don't like it because it is unnecessarily complicated and the
complexity derives only from understand the problem because actually inventing something means that I
have to write all the combinations the combinations can also be skipped if you want because this
game is essentially based on a modulo so I have a ring with all the possible moves and I win
if they are let's say before or after the position of the opponent on this ring so you can
make a module but for three possible values ​​it doesn't make any sense, I just write all the
values ​​that I have named so let's see what a bad problem still better than IntCode from 2019 we have
then x which means that open then the opponent played card so I play scissors and if I play
scissors I have zero points to have lost but I have points to have played scissors which are three if I
then go to the b if I go to the y because the y in fact is the simplest case because the y is
a draw so I have to play a which is 1 plus the score of the draw which is 3 it seems to me yes
this instead is a loss so if it is a loss I already put the plus plus plus if it is a draw
I'm getting lost ok I think I'll do this part offline because it's only about...
so let's pretend that I have implemented this dictionary it makes no sense to be here to write it
part 2 simply the sum of the game score 2 for the p
and I will implement it apart not in the video because there is not a great advantage
see you at the next day bye bye