Welcome to the Advent of Code 2022
Today we will do the exercise of day 1 called Calorie Counting
I will solve it in Python 3.11
The comment will be in Italian but the code will be in English
In the video on YouTube I will publish the subtitles in both languages if I can
Today's exercise, I'm not reading all of it, gives us a list of numbers
separated by an empty line
so for example we have 1000, 2000, 3000, an empty line, 4000, an empty line, other numbers and so on
Each block of numbers separated by an empty line indicates the food that an elf has and their calories
So for example the first elf has a food of 1000 calories, one of 2000 and one of 3000
What the exercise asks us to do is to find the elf that has the most calories in total and calculate how many calories it has in total
So it's pretty easy as an exercise
I start to copy the input to my puzzle
The input changes based on the person, so each one has its input and its result
I copy it and go where I have the repository already initialized
Here I have the initialized git already under version control but I don't have anything else
So let's start to create a folder called input
where I will insert for each day the input of that day, let's call it day01.txt
and paste this thing, it's 2200 lines in my case
At this point I initialize the project using pdm
which I love, it's my new tool to manage dependencies in Python
so I do pdm init
It asks me which interpreter I want, 0 is fine, so python 3.11
I don't expect to use any specific functionality like 3.11 but I have it
Do you want to create a virtualenv with this python? Yes, even if I don't have dependencies for now
Is this project a library that will be loaded on pypi? No
License MIT is fine, my name is fine, my email is fine
ok python, let's do 3.11 but no, let's do a 3.10 at least
I don't expect to use anything particular but it's nice
Ok, I created it, now I create a folder that will contain my project
that I call advent2022
One last thing, I want to ignore the inputs
so I create a nice .gitignore
and inside I put the whole input folder
because I don't want to put it under version control
and that's it, now I can finally solve the exercise
so day01.py, I start to create a function that will be part 1
this function will simply show me the result
so it will return an int
so I do if __name__=="__main__", this is necessary because this code can be imported
as a module or executed directly
so I don't want to execute anything if it's imported as a module
so if for example I write tests later, which maybe I will
I can import it and use it
What I want to do now is simply print the result of part 1
Easy peasy
What do I want to do in the main? I want to read the input first
so what's in the file?
I create a function called get_input
and what's in the file? There is a list of lists of numbers
so every elf is an element of this high-level list
that contains other lists
that are the lists of the calories that that elf has
so I open my file
which will be in input/day01.txt
so input/day01.xt
I call it fr
I create a result that will be this
I start a list, the result, then I will return it directly
so return res
and now what do I do? I will have a partial list
of the calories of this elf
so these calories
I call it partial
but who cares, partial
and I say ok for each line in fr
I say look
if the line
is equal to a new line
I don't remember if this iterator includes the newline or not
so let's say that if
it seems to me that no, so let's say that if the length of the line
in fact you can also do if line
but I don't like it, I prefer to make it explicit
if the line is empty it means that we are observing an empty line
so everything we have seen so far
the partial ends up in the result
so I say res.append
partial and I empty the partial
partial is basically what
I have accumulated for that elf
otherwise I'm seeing some lines with numbers
and then at partial
I add what? I add the version
in the form of int of the line
and we can also test it
because maybe we need to test it first
so what is this called? get_input
I execute it, so look
run python
advent2022
day01
there's only that one... oh noes
I see that here there is a problem because this line
contains the newline
so I have to do this little game here
and I also have to eliminate the last character
so minus one
maybe strip() does the same
let's see
let's try
yes
ok it works
there is one thing missing
maybe you noticed but there is no logic
to manage the last line
so at the end of this round
I only find the penultimate block
because if I never see this line
the last block is ignored
so I have to add this command
also at the end of the cycle
ok so we can see that
in day01
we end up with this 5054 here
the block starts with 2124
that here seems fine
I don't do other tests, I just look at the beginning
just for safety but I think we are there
7844 perfect
ok now let's start with part 1
the input will be this one
so
we call it problem_input
I created a function to get the input because then I will pass it
also to part 2 when I have it
part 1 receives the input
as
as a value so it receives this thing here
this is the problem
we call it problem_input
ok what was the exercise question?
to find the block with the maximum number of calories
it is rather
easy, the problem is to find
the sum of this block so
for every elf I calculate the sum of all the calories
and I find the maximum of these sums so the elf that has more
calories, this is quite
easy, I say look
return the maximum
return, show me
replace the maximum
of what? of the sum of the calories
for every block that I call
calories
in the problem input
note that having used
type int Python knows that this
calories is a list of ints, it knows that sum of calories is a number
and it knows that max is a number so I follow this code
and it tells me 67027
the solution changes
it depends on the user so you could see
a different number and this is correct
let's try to feed this
to the site
good, I mean, I'd be surprised if not
let's continue with the second part
first I want to try some type checking
so I say look pdm add
to install a dependency
dash d to install it as a development dependency
so I just need it to test my code
not to execute the code
and I install mypy which is a type checker
beautiful
so I install it
and not only does it install it in the virtualenv of this project
but it adds it to the dependency block
that is here dev
it is installing mypy 0.991 which at the moment
December 2022, is the latest version
and now I can execute it
I can say look pdm run
inside the virtualenv of this project
pdm run mypy
advent 2022
I made a mistake
oh no there is an error
here at line 4
partial is not defined
what is partial?
it is a list of ints
perfect
and now I execute it again
in strict mode
nothing of this is necessary
I just like to use mypy when I can
perfect
I also install black
it is not necessary
but I like it
I reformatted the code
to be more beautiful
I execute it
it did almost nothing
and now we have the second part of the problem
ok now I'm not going to read the text
I will read it later
it is telling me that
it wants to know the total number of calories
of the first three elves
that have the maximum number of calories
so I don't want to find the maximum
but the three maximum
and then I want to find the sum
so I don't want to find the maximum number of calories
but the number of calories of the first three
so I can no longer use the max function
but it is also quite easy
so I do part 2
which is a copy of part 1
so part 2
now I want to know
the totals
it will be the sum of the calories
for everything that is here
so this is the sum of the calories
for every elf
totals is a list
of ints
so a list of numbers
so this is the calories of the healthy
I want to order it
I can sort it directly
sorted
I don't remember if it is growing or decreasing
it seems to me that it is growing
there is the option
reverse
which gives me the totals
putting the first three
in ascending order
so the first three values will be the three elves
with the maximum number of calories
so I tell it
give me the sum of the totals
it seems to me
that this notation
oh mammamia
it seems to me that this notation
totals 3, replaces the first three
but if I don't know I execute it
totals equal to this
and totals
mammamia
these are the first three
this is exactly what I want
so I execute the code
let's execute black
let's execute mypy
well
let's execute the code again
the second solution
this number here
site
and it's done
thanks for watching
since we are here let's commit
add
pyproject.toml
which is the file created by pdm
which is a standard file
and the .gitignore
in .gitignore, since I'm here, I ignore this
.pdm.toml
so
committed
I make a git status to see that there is nothing strange
what the hell did I write?
no, I want pdm.lock
so gid add pdm.lock
I commit it now
done
day01 completed
I forgot to update the readme
so done, then I'll publish the video
so I put the link
I make a nice amend
well
nothing different
commit --amend
dash a
perfect
now I push
and see you at the next episode
bye everyone